GAURAV CHAUHAN

Mobile: +91-9810550798 / +91-7290035636

mailto:gaurav1205@outlook.com

Current Location/Residence: Gurgaon, Haryana.
Work Location Preference: Gurgaon, Noida.

Work Experience Summary

- Over 14.3 years of extensive experience in Java/J2ee based Application Development, Production Support, Project Management, and System Reliability Engineering for Healthcare and insurance domain applications.
- Working in capacity of Infrastructure and Operations Engineering Manager with Optum Global Solutions (Division of UnitedHealth Group Technology), Gurgaon.
- Good experience with design, development and maintenance of Enterprise applications.
- Handled Site Reliability Engineer (SRE) role for multiple business critical applications
- Good exposure to Cloud (OSE, AWS..) and DevOps tools for build, deploy and production support like Jenkins, Maven, GIT, JIRA, Service Now, HP Service Manager
- Extensive experience in IT service management (ITSM) ITIL processes with complete understanding of service ownership and end to end production process
- Implemented multiple DevOps tools in organizations for application monitoring and alerting like
 Dynatrace 7, Splunk, Grafana, new Relic, HP OpenView, HP Performance Manager etc
- Good exposure on Agile (Scrum/Kanban) based project management.

Experience Summary

| May 2008 – Till Date | ~ 11 Years | Optum Global Solutions (Division of UnitedHealth Group) |
|-----------------------|------------|---|
| April 2005 – May 2008 | 3 Years | Siemens Information Systems Limited. |

Technical Skills

| Languages | Core Java , J2EE Platform (Proficient) |
|---|---|
| Environment | Windows, Unix , Linux (Good) |
| Databases | Oracle 8i/11g, DB2, MonGoDB |
| Java / J2EE Technologies, Framework, Methodologies | JSP, Servlets, JDBC, Struts Framework, Spring (Spring MVC, Spring Boot), Hibernate, Design Pattern, Nodejs, Jasper Reports, Quartz Scheduler, Ajax, Json, Ant, Log4j. |
| UI Technologies | Angular, JQuery, JavaScript |
| X-Technologies | Web Services (SOAP and REST) |
| Scripting Language | Python and Unix Shell. |
| Development Tools | Eclipse, IBM RAD, IntelliJ IDEA, TOAD, SQL Developer |
| Cloud Services | Amazon Cloud Web services, OpenShift Enterprise |
| Web Server/Application Server | Tomcat, Jboss, WebSphere |
| Deployment Tool/Others | Quality Center, Unix, HP Integrated Technology Gateway, Jenkins |
| Monitoring Tools | DCRUM, Openview, DynaTrace, HP Performance Manager, Splunk, Qpasa, AppWatch, Grafana |
| Source version Control Tool | GitHub, SVN, Clear Case, CVS, VSS |
| Production Support Tools | HPSM and Service now for Production support, Putty, WinSCP, FSecure |
| Agile Tools | Rally for Life cycle Management |

Certifications Summary

| PACE (Performance Accelerated Capability Enhancement) – 8 Months Strategy Management Program in with IIM (Indian Institute of Management) Bangalore | 2019 |
|---|------|
| DevOps Professional (DevOps University) | 2019 |
| ITIL V3 Foundation (Certification of IT Service Management) | 2015 |
| Academy of HealthCare Management (AHM – 250) (Certification in Health Care Domain). | 2009 |
| Sun Certified Java Programmer SCJP | |

Educational & Professional Qualification

| Bachelor of Technology, Electronics and Communications Engineering | U.P. Technical University, Lucknow, U.P. | 2000 - 2004 |
|--|--|-------------|
| All India Senior Secondary Certificate Examination | D.A.V Public School, Distt. Meerut, U.P. | 1996 - 1997 |
| All India Secondary Examination. | Kendriya Vidhalaya, Distt. Solan, H.P. | 1994 - 1995 |

Current Responsibilities

Current Role: I O Engineering Manager (Java)

- Work closely with development teams on database design changes to meet business requirements.
 Patch management and version control.
- Detail and able to document low to highly complex functional designs and data structures, to support business and operational requirements.
- Collaborate with, and able to share subject matter knowledge to, business and operational partners during requirements elicitation
- Participate in client technology discussions as necessary
- Executes development processes for the project such as build automation, unit testing, software configuration management and packaging.
- Involve in troubleshooting and debugging critical problems and resolving complex technical issues that may arise.
- Participate in customer interaction and resolves customer issues with software solutions and responds to suggestions for improvements and enhancements and contributes on solution development.
- Prioritize and manage work to critical project time lines in a fast-paced environment
- Leading multiple Agile teams spread across, Gurgaon, Noida and Hyderabad locations.
- Review application landscape Identify any performance issues and requirements of product upgrades. SRE (System Reliability Engineer) expertise to business critical applications.
- Implement DevOps practices within the portfolio
- Actively involved in hiring new talent as well as maintaining/retaining talent within the organization. (I
 am the part of Full Stack Interview Panel of Optum, India)
- Create development road map for Team members as per the organizational goals and individual's capability.

| 1. Project | Identity and Access Management (IAM) | Dec 2017 - Till Now |
|---|---|---|
| Description | Handling multiple applications under IAM portfolio. | |
| | Enterprise SSO – Application is responsible for managing semultiple internal and external application accessed by busing utilize multiple security systems like Ping Federate at backwith OAUTH. | ness and non-business users |
| | IAM Security Operations Center (I-SOC) – The team is be Engineers with focus on application reliability and state applications and identify performance or monitoring gap a application's stability. | oility. Responsible to review |
| | Data Monitoring and Protection (Guardium) – The team is read maintenance of Guardium across all thousands of data responsible to endure data protection and identification if a access related vulnerabilities. | bases in Optum. Guardium is |
| Role | I O Engineering Manager | |
| Technology and Tools Responsibilities | J2EE Technologies, JBoss, Linux, Oracle, MySQL, HPPM, D Grafana, MongoDb, Data protection (Guardium), Python. Designing and Implementation of new business requirements. Closely working wirh business users, I/T, vendors and correquirements. | ents. |
| | Architecture discussion with onshore team and translate implementation. Review application landscape from performance and stal SOC team for action plan in improving monitoring and stal Manage Guardium team from operational standpoint. Guardium as service is being owned by offshore team implementation, service reporting and maintenance. Stakeholder Management | bility standpoint and work with ability. |
| 2. Project | Product LifeCycle Management Center of Excellence (PLM CoE) | Dec 2017 - Nov 2018 |
| Project Description | PLM CoE is responsible to manage the entire lifecycle through engineering design and manufacture, to manufactured products for all application throughout the software being used in organization with latest approved, is upgrade wherever compliance is identified. On an average, product upgrades to bring up all supported products under supports. | service and disposal of organization. Evaluate all the dentify gaps and plan out the team handles more than 300 |
| Technology and Tools | J2EE Technologies, Web Sphere Application server, JBc MySQL, HPPM, Dynatrace, OpenView, Splunk, eLK | oss, IBM HIS, Linux, Oracle, |
| Project Type | Product (WAS, JBOSS, Oracle, MySQL, IHS, Linux/Unix) Up | ograde and Management |
| Role | Technical Project Manager | |
| Responsibilities | Technical Leadership to teams located at Gurgaon and Noi. Analyze and review health status of application from product Work with business and application owners for upgrades. Work on development and implementation of products to be Perform feasibility analysis of products to be upgraded. | ct lifecycle standpoint. |

- Review the analysis and resolve gaps identify by team members.
- Plan and execute the product upgrade deployments/releases.
- Provide production support till warranty period ends after production implementation.
- Managing multiple stakeholders and team involvement in complete lifecycle of product upgrade.

3. Project **Integrated Clinical User Interface (ICUE)** Aug 2015 - Nov 2017 **Project** ICUE platform provides both clinical and non-clinical staff with a consolidated set of Description tools across business segments and a common user experience to perform their tasks more quickly and effectively. This application will be used by all clinical staff performing intake. inpatient coordination, outpatient coordination, coverage review, case and disease management, complex medical conditions, as well as health and wellness management functions. Technology J2EE Technologies, Web Sphere Application server, JBoss, IBM HIS, Linux, Oracle, and Tools MySQL, HPPM, Dynatrace, OpenView, Splunk, eLK, Service Now Project Type Development, Maintenance and Production Support Role **Technical Project Manager** Responsibilities • Understand business requirement, Design and develop modules assigned to my work Lead discussions business, system and business analysts for requirement gathering and clarification calls • Also play the role of System Reliability Engineer (SRE), to ensure high uptime of application and quickest restoration to minimize business impact. • Highly active involvement in War room for service restoration. Involved in setup and implementation of Highly Available environment for application. • Plan and execute the product upgrade deployments/releases. Close Monitoring of application using various monitoring tools and take immediate action to avoid any anticipated downtime. Perform Root Cause Analysis on issues that have caused or potentially could have caused downtime to application to avoid recurrence. Work with infrastructure and architecture teams to analyze capacity needs of current infra.

| 4. Project | UnitedHealth Group Portal Applications | May 2008 – July 2015 |
|------------------------|---|---|
| Project Description | Worked on multiple UHG portals, being used by multiproviders, employers and brokers. These portals are highly standpoint as these are being used by end users who Keeping these application stable and highly available is critical. | u critical from UHG business bought insurance of UHG. |
| Role | Sr. Software Developer → Associate Lead → Technical Pro | ject Lead |
| Technology and Tools | J2EE (JSP1.2, Servlet, Struts1.1, Spring (ioc), iBatis, Wel 6.0, Websphere 5.1, Rational Clearcase for content material Oracle 10 as Backend Systems. | · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · |
| Project Type | Development and Production Support | |
| Responsibilities | As the Project Lead my responsibilities includes: Design and Development of modules assigned to me. Track day to day operations and deliveries, includes statue. Maintenance and Enhancement of the Application. Coordinate with Stakeholders and system analysts for new Provide Production Support to live application. Provide immediate fix or Workaround for any high priority. | w Enhancement. |

| Resolve the priority issue with proper fix within the time specified in SLA. |
|--|
| Resume or Rerun batch job on UNIX server, if it gets failed. |
| Generate Daily Report for checking status of Application and other associated |
| backend system |
| Coordinate with IT and business partners for analyzing any critical issues. |
| Provide support to team for implementing enhancements and Problem tickets, |
| targeted for next Release |
| Metrics and SLA reporting. |

| 5. Project | Portal for Department of Labor, South Africa Siyaya Admin Project. Employment Equity (EE) System, NSFDIS, CIPA (Production Support project) Apr 2005 – May 2008 |
|------------------------|--|
| Project Description | Siyaya Web Portal being developed for Department of Labor, Govt. of South Africa, which maintains the information about all the Commercial employers as well as all Individual Organizations (Domestic employers) for unemployment insurance fund. This project will be ported as a web based enterprise application, wherein, employers can come and register themselves on DOL server. |
| Organization | Siemens Information Systems Limited |
| Technology and Tools | J2EE (JSP1.2, Struts1.1, Servlet, EJB), XML, XSLT, Oracle 9i, Eclipse 3.1 IDE, TOAD IDE, JBoss4.0 Application Server, OpenLDAP repository server. |
| Role | Senior Systems Engineer |
| Project Type | Development and Production Support |

Onsite Exposure

- Played key role and represented the organization during multiple onshore assignments. Involved in Technical consultancy, Project Planning and Stakeholder Management in 2015
 - 2 months of business trip to client location at Texas, USA to transition project to Optum in 2015
 - 1.5 Years as Service Coordinator at UnitedHealth Group, New Jersey, USA for Development and enhancement and production support project in 2010-2011.
 - 1.5 Years as Technical Consultant Department of Labor, South Africa on behalf of Siemens, India in 2006 2007